{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A memorial to honor soldiers killed while serving on these vessels was built by the WarGravesCommission.ThefirsttimetheseweaponswereusedinWorldWarOneresulted in the sinking of the HMS Pathfinder. One ofthesevesselsunderthecommandofIronCross winner Otto Weddigen [[VEH-dih-gehn]] sank the so-called \"Live Bait Squadron\"inasingle hour. Fortenpoints,identifythesenavalsubmarinesoperatedbytheGermanEmpireduring the First and Second World Wars. ANSWER:U-Boats (acceptU-Boots; orUnterseeboots) (2) While in Paris, this man met with scientists Michel-Eugene Chevreul [[shev-RUHL]] and Ogdon Rood, who inspired his theories on the \"language of color.\" This developer of chromo-luminarism depicted the raucous Moulin Rouge [[moo-LAHN ROOZH]] in The Can-Can, and he was rejected from the Paris Salon after completing the massive Bathers at Asnières[/a] [[ahz-NYEHR]]. For ten points, name this French advocate of pointillism, on display in his [i]A Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grande Jatte[[ZHAHT]].",
      "answer": "Georges PierreSeurat"
    },
    {
      "question": "The year after this disaster, Thomas Edison produced the short film The Cost of Carelessness. This disaster was worsened by the fact that Max Blanck andIsaacHarris,who owned the factory at which this event took place, lockedthedoorstopreventunauthorized breaks. The American Society of Safety Professionals was founded in the wake of this industrial disaster. For ten points, name this 1911 fire which killed hundreds of garment workers in New York City. ANSWER:Triangle ShirtwaistFactory Fire (4) The case Tinker v. Des Moines concerned wearing an armband within these institutions to protest the Vietnam War. Horace Mann promoted a series of reforms concerning these institutions that included gradual secularization and professionalization. The Race to the Top and NoChildLeftBehindprogramsaffectedtheseinstitutions.Brownv. Board of Education mandated desegregation within, for ten points, what institutions in which children learn? ANSWER:Schools (accept Public or PrivateSchools;accept CommonSchoolMovement; accept Elementary, Middle, or HighSchools; acceptEducationbefore mentioned) 2021-22 C Set History (5) This politician's daughter, Sara, launched a \"Courage and Compassion\" campaign meant to edge out her rival, Antonio Trillanes [[tree-YAH-nehs]]. This man has been linked to the extrajudicial killing of criminals committed by the \"Davao [[dah-\"VOW\"]] Death Squad.\" Participants in the People Power Revolution attemptedtoblockthispresidentfrom allowing the burial of Ferdinand Marcos in a national cemetery in Manila. For ten points, name this Filipino president who took office in 2016.",
      "answer": [
        "RodrigoDuterte] or RodrigoRoaDuterte",
        "acceptPRRD"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Josephus[[joh-SEE-fus]]claimedthismonarchledafutilethirteen-yearsiegeofTyre [[\"TIRE\"]], later coming to terms with its king, Ithobaal III [[ith-oh-BALE \"the third\"]]. This restorer of the Ishtar Gate supposedly blinded the king of Judah, Zedekiah, for rebelling against his rule. In the biblical tradition, this Chaldean [[kahl-DEE-un]] king cast Shadrach [[SHAD-rak]], Meshach [[MEE-shak]], and Abednego [[ah-BED-neh-go]] into the fiery furnace and had his dreams interpreted by Daniel. For ten points, name this long-reigning king of the Neo-Babylonian Empire. ANSWER:Nebuchadnezzar[[neh-buh-kahd-NEH-zar]] II(orNabû-kudurri-uṣur; accept Nebuchadnezzarthe Great) (7) In this city's Congress of Peace, it was determined that the Holy See shouldhaveits sovereignty revoked. The League of Nations headquarters was moved from London to this neutral city in 1920, remaining so until the League's dissolution. French reformer John Calvin led a semi-theocratic government in this city during the 16th century. A convention that regulates the rules of war is named for, for ten points, what Swiss city? ANSWER:Geneva(acceptGenève; orGenf; orGinevra) (8) While head of the Provisional Theatre, Bedřich Smetana [[BED-ur-zhik SMEH-tah-nah]] returned this composer's first draft of the historical comedy King and Charcoal Burner after declaring it unperformable. His time in Iowa among fellow Central Europeans led to this composer writing the American Quartet. African-American spirituals influenced this man's composition, Symphony from the New World. Bohemian folk music often inspired, for ten points, which Czech composer'sSlavonic Dances?",
      "answer": "AntonínDvořák] or AntonínLeopoldDvořák 2021-22 C Set History"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man condemned commercial dishonesty in Boston in his sermon Theopolis Americana. This minister wrote to the judge William Stoughton [[\"STOW\"-ten]] to congratulate him on the destruction of \"devilism\" during the Salem Witch Trials. This religious figure's father, Increase, served as president of Harvard in the late17thcentury.A contemporary of Jonathan Edwards, for ten points, who was this prominent New England Puritan during the First Great Awakening? ANSWER:CottonMather(prompt on \"Mather\") (10) This man credits his relative lack of injury during his playing career to training in aikido withactorBruceLee.Thisbasketballplayerparticipatedinthe\"GameoftheCentury\" under coach John Wooden, being held to 15 points, in part due to a scratched cornea. This athlete, whopioneeredthe\"Skyhook\"technique,boycottedthe1968OlympicGamesshortly after his conversion to Islam. For ten points, name this Milwaukee Bucks and Los Angeles Lakers legend, a Hall of Fame Center.",
      "answer": [
        "KareemAbdul-Jabbar",
        "Ferdinand Lewis\"Lew\"Alcindor, Jr. 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The only known source oftheSafaitic[[sah-fah-IH-tik]]languageisfromthiskindof art piece. There areseveralancientRomanexamplesofthisartformfoundinPompeii,often accompanied by lewd jokes. The use of stencils for this art form developed inFranceinthe 1980s. Commercialized by artists such as Banksy, for ten points, what generally unsanctioned art typically takes the form of writing or drawing on a wall or some other surface? ANSWER:Graffiti(orGraffito; prompt on \"Street Art\") BONUS: This Haitian-American artist first rose to prominence as part of the graffiti duo SAMO [[\"SAME\"-oh]] with Al Diaz. This activist created the Untitleddepictionsofskullsand died of a heroin overdose at 27.",
        "answer": "Jean-MichelBasquiat] 2 After this judge was elected head of his country's supreme court, he rapidly succeeded the conservative Ignacio Comonfort ] as president. This man led the liberals during the War of the Reform and asserted himself as the legitimate president after theFrenchInterventioninstalledEmperorMaximilianinMexicoCity.Forten points, name this first indigenouspresidentofMexico,whosenamegracesacitythatshares a border with El Paso, Texas. ANSWER: BenitoJuárez] or Benito PabloJuárezGarcía"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "JuarezwasborninthissouthernMexicanstate,whichisalsohometomanyZapotec and Mixtec groups. Hernán Cortés became Marquess [[mahr-KESS]] of the Valley of [this modern state]. ANSWER:Oaxaca[[wuh-HAH-kah]] (or Free and SovereignState ofOaxaca; accept Huāxyacac[[wash-YAH-kak]]) 2021-22 C Set History (3) Though the earliest form of this science is seen in the 6th century BC morphology studies of Indian philosopher Panini, this field's modern form dates to Ferdinand de Saussure's [[sow-SOORS]] insistence on synchronic analysis todistinguishitfromphilology. Jacob Grimm wrote the first work in this field for German, which exhaustively codified its grammar. Dealing with concepts like syntax and semantics, for ten points, what science is the study of languages? ANSWER:Linguistics(prompt on \"Philology\" beforementioned) BONUS: This contemporary linguist and anarchist thinker began working at MIT in 1955. This man's seminal work Syntactic Structures elaborated on his teacher Zellig Harris's generative grammar theory and became a foundational text of cognitive science.",
        "answer": "NoamChomskyor Avram NoamChomsky"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Castro v. Superior Court decision inspired one of these people, Oscar Acosta, to write Revolt of the Cockroach People. Boxer and poet Rodolfo Gonzales led the \"Crusade for Justice,\" which agitated for the cultural development of these people. The Delano Grape Strike of the 1960s was led by a man of this ethnicity who popularized the phrase \"Si, Se Puede\" [[see-seh-PWEH-deh]]. Labor leader Cesar Chavez was from, for ten points, which Hispanic minority in the U.S.? ANSWER:Mexican-American (acceptChicanos; prompton \"Latine,\" \"Latino,\" \"Latinx,\" or \"Hispanic\") BONUS: Oscar Acosta served as the inspiration for Dr. Gonzo in this author's Fear and Loathing in Las Vegas. He later wrote Fear and Loathing on the Campaign Trail concerning the Nixon re-election bid.",
        "answer": "Hunter StocktonThompson 5 Governor William Berkeley createdabicamerallegislaturemadeupofthisbodyand the Council of theState.ShortlybeforebeingdissolvedbyLordDunmore,PatrickHenrytold this bodyto\"Givemelibertyorgivemedeath.\"Thislegislativeentitywasfirstestablishedin 1619 in Jamestown and later moved to Williamsburg. For ten points, name this legislative body of Colonial Virginia. ANSWER: House ofBurgesses"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Much of the Virginia House of Burgesses supported this rebel leader who burned down Jamestown in 1676 and temporarily deposed the aforementioned governor, William Berkeley.",
        "answer": "NathanielBaconacceptBacon's Rebellion 2021-22 C Set History"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the aftermath of a revolt by this figure, the freedman Polyclitus [[pah-lee-KLY-tuss]] led an investigation that deposed governor Gaius Suetonius Paulinus [[\"GUY\"-us swee-TOH-nee-us paw-\"LIE\"-nuss]]. This woman's husband, Prasutagus [[prah-soo-TAY-gus]], originally submitted to vassal status duringtheconquestsofClaudius. With the Trinovantes [[trih-noh-VAN-teez]], this woman's combined tribal army burned down bothEboracum[[eh-BOR-sh-kum]]andLondinium.Fortenpoints,namethisqueenof the Iceni [[\"eye\"-SEE-nee]] tribe who led Britons in a 1st century revolt against the Roman Empire. ANSWER:Boudicca(acceptBuddug; acceptBoadicea)) BONUS: Boudicca's Revolt occurred during the reign of this Julio-Claudian Roman emperor who built theDomus Aurea. ANSWER:NeroClaudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus (7) The White Army-aligned Alasha Orda controlled this modernnation'sareaforthree years before surrendering to the USSR. The Soviet Space Program launched the Vostok missions from this country's Baikonur [[BYE-koh-noor]] Cosmodrome. The Russian-led Commonwealth of Independent States was established by an agreement signed in this nation known as the AlmatyProtocol.NursultanNazarbayev[[nah-zar-BYE-eff]]onceruled, for ten points, what former Soviet republic in Central Asia?",
        "answer": [
          "Republic ofKazakhstan orQazaqstan Respublikasy",
          "acceptKazakhSoviet Socialist Republic",
          "orQazaqKeńestik Sosıalıstik"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Before being exiled to Mexico, this rival of Stalin and reformer of the Red Army spent much of 1928 in exile in Kazakhstan.",
        "answer": [
          "LeonTrotsky",
          "Lev DavidovichBronstein"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Lead-up to the American Revolutionary War",
      "prompt": "Concerning the lead-up to the American Revolutionary War, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Monarch who imposed duties and other restrictions on the American colonies.",
          "answer": "KingGeorge III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Irish writer ofReflections on the Revolutionin Francewho urged Parliament to make peace with the colonies.",
          "answer": "EdmundBurke"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Charlemagne",
      "prompt": "Concerning the rule and legacy of Charlemagne [[SHAR-luh-MANE]], name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Title he took following his crowning by the Pope, later used by medieval rulers of Germany.",
          "answer": [
            "HolyRoman EmperororEmperorof theRomans",
            "alternate answers likeEmperorofRome"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "843 treaty which split his realm between his grandsons.",
          "answer": "Treaty ofVerdun] 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Malaysia",
      "prompt": "Concerning the nation of Malaysia, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Wealthy city-state which was expelled in 1965.",
          "answer": "Republic ofSingapore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Powerful medieval state which shares its name with a \"Strait\" separating the Malay peninsula from Sumatra.",
          "answer": "Sultanate ofMalacca"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighbor who annexed its northern reaches during World War Two as a member of the Japanese Co-Prosperity Sphere.",
          "answer": "Kingdom ofThailandorSiam"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A 1980 film made about this caseisentitled[itsplaintiff's]Trumpet.Thiscase selectively incorporated the Sixth (20 pts)",
        "Amendment across the United States. The plaintiff in this case, who hadrobbedaFloridapoolhall,wasnotgrantedcounseldue to having only committed a felony, as opposed to a capital (10 pts)",
        "offense. For ten points, name this 1963 Supreme Court decision that established the legal right to counsel for defendants who are unable to afford their own attorneys. ANSWER:Gideonv. Wainwright(orClarence E.Gideonv. Louie L. Wainwright, Corrections Director) (2) A boldly polyphonic opera named for this character was originallyperformed at the 1607 Carnival for the court in Mantua and istheearlieststill-performedopera of Monteverdi. (+) A lampoon of this character's story by Jacques Offenbach [[OH-fen-bahk]] includes the \"Galop Infernal,\" a song later adapted to the can-can dance, and is titled for [this character] in the Underworld. (*) For ten points,namethis musically-gifted Greek hero, whose love for Eurydice [[yoo-RIH-dih-see]] is the subject of many operas. ANSWER:Orpheus[[OHR-fee-us]] (acceptL'Orfeo; acceptOrpheusin the Underworld) (3) While serving under this man, a young P. G. T. Beauregard provided vital reconnaissance during the Battle of Cerro Gordo. Shortly before his death, this man formulated the Anaconda (+) Plan as a way to cut-off the Confederacy from naval trade. The amphibious seizure of Veracruz by this man facilitated his march on Mexico (*) City during the Mexican-AmericanWar.Fortenpoints,namethisone-timeWhig presidential candidate and general known as \"Old Fuss 'n' Feathers.\""
      ],
      "answer": "WinfieldScott"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Using the codename Bolek, thismanlikelyinformedonhisfellowworkingmen regarding dissident matters such as listening to Radio Free Europe. This electrician led a strike of (20 pts)",
        "17,000 workers at the Lenin Shipyards in Gdansk [[guh-DANSK]]. This man achieved semi-free elections following theRoundTableAgreementsheldin Warsaw. The leader of the trade union (10 pts)",
        "Solidarity was, for ten points, what first president of a democratic Poland?"
      ],
      "answer": "LechWałęsa] be lenienton pronunciation 2021-22 C Set History"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A vision of the bodhisattva [[BOH-dee-SAHT-vah]] Guanyin [[GWAHN-YIN]] prompted this ruler to offer Buddhist leader Deshin Shekpa armies to reunite Tibet. This future ruler perpetrated the Jingnan [[JING-NAHN]] Rebellion, which overthrew his nephew, the (20 pts)",
        "Jianwen[[JYAHN-WEN]]emperor,withthehelpofmilitaryofficers including Zheng He [[ZHUNG HUH]]. This emperor began construction on the Forbidden City after moving his capital to Beijing. The Ming (10 pts)",
        "Treasure fleet voyages were deployed by, for ten points, which 15th century Chinese emperor? ANSWER:Yongle[[YONG-LUH]] Emperor (acceptZhu Di) (6) The oldest still existing one of these instrumentsisnamedforCharlesIX[[the ninth]] of France, whofirstmass-orderedthemfromItalyforhiscourtmusicians.The searchforthemostaccomplishedvirtuosoofthisinstrumentisheldyearlyduringthe (+) Premio Paganini in Genoa. One of these instruments named Soil, which is in the possession of Itzhak [[EET-zahk]] (*) Perlman, was created by the accomplished luthier Antonio Stradivari [[strah-dih-VAH-ree]]. For ten points, name this stringed instrument which is smaller than a viola. ANSWER:Violin(accept theFiddle) (7) This location was first discovered by a European when Portuguese explorer Vicente Pegado went searching for gold between the Zambezi and Limpopo rivers. This African (+) citadel likely served as the western terminus of a trade route that reached the Swahili Coast and extended to medievalChina.TheShona(*)peoplebuilt, for the point, what ancient city which shares its name with a southern African nation governed from Harare [huh-RAH-reh]]?"
      ],
      "answer": "GreatZimbabwe"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While under the engineer Lucius Cornelius Balbus, this man led the artillery corps during Caesar's Gallic campaign. This man innovated the technology of the hypocaust[[HY-poh-kost]],whichprovidedcentral (20 pts)",
        "heatingtovillasandbaths.This polymath stated that all buildings should have \"Utility, Strength, and Beauty\" in his multi-volume workDeArchitectura[[ar-kee-tek-TOO-rah]].Leonardo (10 pts)",
        "DaVincidrew a figure of a \"Man\" named for, for ten points, which ancient Roman architect?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "MarcusVitruviusPollio",
        "theVitruvianMan 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    }
  ]
}